<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lab &amp; Data Science</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Lab &amp; Data Science</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Motivation</title>
      <link>/2020/02/motivation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/motivation/</guid>
      <description>I currently manage a small laboratory. Recently we unexpectedly had to conduct several method validations in a matter of weeks. While working through these validations, it became apparent how dependent labs like mine, and even larger laboratories are on manufacturers with respect to method validations and data analytics. Statistics have fallen by the wayside, despite it being an integral part of the laboratory.
My goal here is to share what I’ve learned on how to collect, interpret and interact with data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistics Basics</title>
      <link>/2020/02/statistics-basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/statistics-basics/</guid>
      <description>Statistics is inherent in laboratory work since our primary product is data, yet so little emphasis is placed on it in medical technology schools. In this post we will cover basic statistical concepts that are commonly encountered in the laboratory.
We will first study probability distributions. In the process we will learn about measures of central tendency (i.e. mean, mode, median) and measures of dispersion (i.e. variance, standard deviation, coefficient of variation).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deming and Passing-Bablok Regressions</title>
      <link>/2020/02/deming-and-passing-bablok-regressions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/deming-and-passing-bablok-regressions/</guid>
      <description>Deming and Passing-Bablok regressions are used to compare two quantitative methods. They are used to compare a reference method to the new method. Depending on the data structure, one of these two regression methods is used a part of a validation study.
Deming and Passing-Bablok regressions are variations of an ordinary-least-squares (OLS) linear regression. In this post we will discuss Deming and Passing-Bablok regressions. Before we get there however, we will first touch on OLS regression.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>Hello and welcome! My name is Adrian Bandolon. I have been a Medical Technologist for over 15 years . In that time I have earned a PhD in Marine Biology and more recently, a Master&amp;rsquo;s in Computer Science specializing in Data Science.
Currently, I manage a laboratory that provide services for a free-standing ED in South Texas. This blog will focus on statistics and data science applications in the laboratory and in my day-to-day.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>