<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Lab &amp; Data Science</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Lab &amp; Data Science</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID19 Forecasting</title>
      <link>/2020/03/covid19-forecasting/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/03/covid19-forecasting/</guid>
      <description>A COVID19 Global Forecasting competition has been launched in Kaggle. I would love to participate in the competition, but just do not have the time. My work at the hospital takes precedence. My aim for the time being is to describe the progression of COVID19 as it sweeps across the world. I still have much to learn about modelling epidemic/pandemic progression. An attempt at forecasting will follow later.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Method Verification</title>
      <link>/2020/03/method-verification/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/03/method-verification/</guid>
      <description>Every now and again we have to perform method verification studies. Method verification is required when implementing new tests, when a new instrument is installed or if a method is changed. In rare cases, a verification study is also needed when changing collection tube manufacturer or tube additive.1
For method verification studies, help is usually provided by the test manufacturer. They will typically send a technician that will run all the samples, crunch all the data and provide a report.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R Basics</title>
      <link>/2020/03/r-basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/03/r-basics/</guid>
      <description>When I was a graduate student most, if not all statistical computing was done either through SAS or SPSS. Both of these software packages were proprietary and licenses had to be bought by the university for its students. At that time, the license for SAS was around $1,000. Too expensive for a graduate student. Then along came R, an open-source, meaning free software package.
R will take time to learn, but it will be worth the effort.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deming and Passing-Bablok Regressions</title>
      <link>/2020/02/deming-and-passing-bablok-regressions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/deming-and-passing-bablok-regressions/</guid>
      <description>Deming and Passing-Bablok regressions are used to compare two quantitative methods. They are used to compare a reference method to the new method. Depending on the qualities of the data, one of these two regression methods is used a part of a validation study.
Deming and Passing-Bablok regressions are variations of an ordinary-least-squares (OLS) linear regression. In this post we will discuss Deming and Passing-Bablok regressions. Before we get there however, we will first touch on OLS regression.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistics Basics</title>
      <link>/2020/02/statistics-basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/statistics-basics/</guid>
      <description>Statistics is inherent in laboratory work since our primary product is data, yet so little emphasis is placed on it in medical technology schools. In this post we will cover basic statistical concepts that are commonly encountered in the laboratory.
We will study probability distributions. In the process we will learn about measures of central tendency (i.e. mean, mode, median) and measures of dispersion (i.e. variance, standard deviation, coefficient of variation).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Motivation</title>
      <link>/2020/02/motivation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/motivation/</guid>
      <description>I currently manage a small laboratory. Recently we unexpectedly had to conduct several method validations in a matter of weeks. While working through these validations, it became apparent how dependent labs like mine, and even larger laboratories are on manufacturers with respect to method validations and data analytics. Statistics have fallen by the wayside, despite it being an integral part of the laboratory.
My goal here is to share what I’ve learned on how to collect, interpret and interact with data.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>